h
ah
[Music]
hello and welcome back everybody Welcome
to the ask AIT show today we are doing
episode 235 and I hope you're doing or
you're all doing very well so before we
take the questions which I'm going to
take from the comments uh let's let's
see who all is there on the live chat as
always I can see mahita buetti ABI
chandel 05 right winger surender Gupta
Amar Singh u geopolitical dub Sam
tripati VII Manar 21 TOA
Salam Barat first aush Mr 88 sh Hari
Arun um hardik rohil Noel k k tar Alvin
Rodriguez manmat tiari Arian Raj ombe
Kiker hello KY kgy Gamers anuli Mary
skibidi Sunil chaare Kip Sarma just ant
buhan shha karney Prashant mahasagar Mr
Redbird abishek
haa kishar Raj in depth gorov satas
Swami s Abhijit Supreme Lord KY kgy
Gamers vinit Sam Savant pray Paul from
Kolkata bries SK sakeet katari Krishna
goind Alfred ragunath buev Rai from the
Surinam Netherlands uh sakit U Reika
humble who else do we have Grim Reaper
plays abishek shast sand s Mitra Mitra
prar Gupta Anita M Lovin happy holy
everybody body uh Philip
Shimon keska Ashish
Singh uh and so many other people OAS
swini nitu Sharma Neil raal Prashant
mahasagar and everybody else all right
all right all right let's get going with
the questions now and we're going to
take some questions we're going to take
the questions that you have asked in the
comments and afterwards if there is some
more time we'll take some questions from
the live chat as well as always there's
a lot of questions so where do we begin
let's begin with question number one
what's question number one it is by
Krishna of the Surinam Netherlands how
reliable is carbon dating and what are
the strengths and weaknesses of carbon
dating yes carbon dating is integral to
our study of history and to historical
research archaeological
research so what is carbon dating how
reliable is carbon dating and what are
the strengths and weaknesses so carbon
dating is also called radiocarbon dating
or Carbon 14 dating and it's one of the
most widely used methods for determining
the age of uh archaeological materials
organic materials and this works for
materials that are approximately up to
50,000 years old and this method was
developed I think in the first half of
the 20th century maybe in in the 1940s
okay and the technique it uh it it
measures the the decay of a carbon
isotope called carbon 14 it's a
radioactive isotope and by doing this
you are estimating the time since the
depth of the organ of of the organism or
of the organic material so there are
three kinds there are three
isotopes that we know of of carbon
carbon 12 carbon 13 carbon 14 carbon 12
has six protons six neutrons six
electrons and the radi nucle carbon 14
has eight neutrons it has a half life of
about 6,000 or so years maybe less than
that maybe 5,700 or so years so carbon
dating is used to estimate to a very
precise degree the age of
organic remains so if you give me a
piece of rock and tell me that let's
carbon dat this it's not going to work
because rock is not
organic it is an
inorganic uh substance material it's a
rock but if you have a piece of bone if
you have a piece of wood if you have sea
shell this all this stuff is organic
remains and you can carbon date that so
it's effective in dating uh organic
remains like like these and it can give
you a very good estimate as to how old
the this material is so that's the
strength of carbon dating it works
pretty accurately for organic materials
like wood and bones and such things up
to an up to about 50,000 years before
today okay so the are the strengths the
weaknesses is that first of all uh it
only works for samples that are up to
50,000 years old for older samples it
doesn't work why is that because of the
halflife of this carbon uh 14 isotope
the halflife is about 5,700 800 years
and because of that uh it only works for
samples up to up to 50,000 years old and
Beyond this there's very little carbon
14 that's left in the in older samples
which makes uh the dating uh accurate
dating more challenging so that's the
weakness of carbon dating and then there
are other weaknesses like samples can be
contaminated by contaminated by external
sources of carbon like modern pollution
or ancient carbon from fossil fuels
which may have contaminated your sample
and there's also the problem of
variations in the atmospheric carbon 14
fluctuations because of various reasons
like fossil fuel burning and nucle
nuclear testing uh above ground nuclear
testing which has which has happened a
lot in the past Century in the 20th
century especially the 1950s 1960s Etc
uh this significantly increased the
amount of carbon 14 in the atmosphere
it's called the bomb pulse it's called
the bomb pulse or the bomb Surge and
this I believe almost doubled the amount
of carbon 14 in the atmosphere in the
20th century and that can obviously
cause cause problems if you don't
account for the bomb for the bomb surge
bomb pulse so all these are the
challenges which you have to address
when you doing Carbon 14 dating so
Carbon 14 dating for
pre-1950s samples is reasonably
unaffected by nuclear testing but
samples later than that you have to
account for the U nuclear testing uh
bomb surge or bomb pulse in the
atmosphere so yeah it's it's challenging
and uh it's accuracy the accuracy of
radiocarbon dating uh depends on how
carefully you've prepared the sample how
much you've ensured that there is no
contamination and how well you have
calibrated to account for historical
variations in the amount of carbon 14 in
the atmospheric uh in the atmosphere so
these are the strengths and weaknesses
of carbon dating radiocarbon dating or
Carbon 14 dating it's a pretty good uh
technique that we have for about for
samples that are up to 50,000 years
old okay questions about Pakistan for a
change I usually don't take questions
about Pakistan but yes things have
happened of late so let's talk about
what's happening in Pakistan Sam asks
who is funding and arming military
militant groups like The balistan
Liberation Army and the TQ a Taliban
Pakistan enabling attacks like the jafer
express uh thing that happened there in
Miss strikes in kber pakun what
triggered these attacks was it
opposition to the China Pakistan
economic Corridor control over
balochistan's fast resources or deeper
geopolitical tensions with over 340
hostages rescued are you sure about that
that's what the Pakistani military is
claiming and casualties between 21 and
28 29 people that's again a claim by the
Pakistani army you have to take it with
with a bucket full of salt and why is
the Pakistani foreign Ministry blaming
India what are the broader Regional
geopolitical
implications nice language uh P
mahasagar says is the recent train
hijack in baluchistan and the whole
baluchistan Freedom Movement from behind
the doors funded by India baluchi or do
we get themselves or is the US
supporting them or is China behind it or
maybe somebody else what's behind this
sidart says as trains are getting
hijacked in Pakistan by The baluchistan
Liberation Army are we going to see a
free baluchistan in the near future so
first of all let me categorically say
this there is no Indian hand behind this
India does not support any um any kind
of military or other action that would
Target civilians okay India doesn't do
that and India doesn't uh support any
insurgencies in foreign Nations we are a
peaceful peaceloving nation and we India
has been at the receiving end of
terrorism for decades Pakistan and US
sponsored and and funded Terror ISM for
decades in the 20th century and also in
the 21st century so we having been at
the receiving end of this would never do
anything that would lead to similar
consequences in other nations even if
it's a nation like Pakistan which is the
global epicenter of terrorism we would
not do that so let me categorically say
this India there is no Indian hand
behind this the Pakistani foreign
ministry will say such things they are a
bunch of liars okay sadly it's true it's
true um and they will try and cover up
their
shortcomings and their intelligence
failures and their military weakness and
other weaknesses by blaming India for
what happened so there is no Indian hand
behind this whatsoever the Pakistani
government may make such accusations
nothing surprising about it but they are
doing it only to cover up their
weaknesses and their shortcomings and
their failures they're catastrophic
failures so there was this uh all of
this is being asked in the country text
of the recent hijacking of the Jaffer
Express in baluchistan near the in the
Bolan region by the Freedom Fighters of
of baluchistan The baluchistan
baluchistan Liberation Army so what they
did is they uh uh they hijacked this
train they stopped it they identified
all the civilians all the men women
children elderly Etc they asked them to
leave and go go go to safety and there
happened to be a large number maybe more
than 28 80 uh more than 280 Pakistani uh
army or military personnel on the train
and those individuals were were captured
by The baluchistan Liberation Army and
the bla then then gave the Pakistani
government or military whatever it is uh
a time of 48 hours to release all the uh
civilians who have been illegally uh uh
detained and thrown into prison by the
Pakistani military you know lot does
this oper operation going on in
baluchistan so uh they gave them 48
Hours the bla gave the Pakistani
military 48 hours to release these
prisoners and that did not happen and
then the bla has released a statement
saying that they have uh executed those
280 plus uh Pakistani military
personnel um but the Pakistani
government and Military will say that
they have they have rescued all the
hostages and uh so on so forth so there
are two versions of what's happening the
Pakistan military will say that there
have been very few casualties we've
rescued all the hostages and just a few
people have died and we have liquidated
all the balistan Liberation Army Freedom
Fighters that's what the Pakistani
military will claim the bla has put out
a statement saying that something very
very different and what I just said who
do you believe it's up to you who who
you want to believe obviously we don't
have boots on the ground we don't have
eyes on the ground over there so we
don't really know what's happening
there's a lot of footage coming out
that's being that's being put out by the
bla that um I would rather say don't see
it because it is disturbing and uh
there's Bloodshed in it so I would
rather I would recommend not to see that
in case you're sensitive and uh so on so
I would tend to believe what the bla is
saying and not what the Pakistani
military is saying the Pakistani
military has a long standing history of
of lying about their casualties of of
not owning up to their own Dead uh
military personnel we have seen that
over and over
again um so that's what has happened now
the question is uh who's funding it
who's F funding the baluchistan Freedom
Movement and so on look I don't know
okay I can only speculate is the us
doing it well Pakistan is a us wasal why
would the US want Pakistan to be
destabilized right good question yes uh
okay let's let's take a look at where
balasan is on the map because we are
discussing it so let us uh do
uh that let's take a look at the map
where's the map we'll see the
map so we're looking at the western part
of India present day temporarily
Pakistan and this region here okay in
the middle of the screen is more or less
bistan I can I can search for it
beluchistan beluchistan
beluchistan
beluchistan that's it
and yeah it won't give you a demarcation
if I say Pakistan just for the sake of
doing
that once again it is not giving you any
boundaries but this region is
baluchistan and it it's very
interestingly the map is
putting Iran actually Center in the
center of the of the screen which is
interesting this region of Iran because
baluchistan is a region that's
historically you know half of it is
currently in Pakistan half of it is
currently in
Iran so um that is the deal now what was
the question that was asked uh who could
be behind this right so look the US
would probably not be behind this
because Pakistan is a is a US vasal US
asset why would they destabilize their
own asset could the Taliban be behind
this well Taliban hates Pakistan we know
that and they have this big territorial
dispute with Pakistan because the the
pashun want to uh regain the K Paka
region that has historically been theirs
um so yes it it kind of would make sense
for the Taliban to Aid the BL that kind
of would make sense but then you also
have to understand the complication
which results from the fact that the
Taliban receives allegedly between 30 to
50 to 100 million in cash from the US
per week which means the Taliban the
Afghan Taliban is a US
asset but geopolitics is complicated so
why despite being a us I said they may
be funding The balistan Liberation Army
it's possible would Iran fund the bla
what well it's complicated and probably
they would not do it because half of
baluchistan is in Iran so if you're
funding The baluchistan Liberation
movement in Pakistan it would also
create a similar sentiment in the
Iranian portion of baluchistan and Iran
has already it already has enough even
enough headaches to deal with so I don't
think Iran would would do that so maybe
the Taliban the afan Taliban could be
behind this I'm just guessing I don't
know it's a possibility but I will
categorically deny any Indian
involvement in this will we see a free
baluchistan in the future sooner or
later we will see a free beluchistan in
the future sooner or later there are so
many internal forces in Pakistan that uh
seek to to well which seek to pull
Pakistan apart at the seams and it's
only because of external invol external
interference that Pakistan is uh remains
United temporarily as an artificial
geopolitical uh entity
it's because of the support of outside
powers that the Pakistan military
continues to exist because it has no
source of income it is Pakistan is a
nearly bankrupt Nation it has always
been on the verge of bankruptcy
bankruptcy the past 20 30 years right um
so it's because of us support that the
Pakistani military currently exists
before that it was Chinese support now
it's us support us is the Big Daddy so
as long as Pakistan has geopolitical
significance and you use for the us as a
counterbalance or destabilizing factor
towards
India not a nice thing but it is what it
is as long as that that utility is there
Pakistan will continue to exist as a
single entity once India becomes more
powerful and Pakistan becomes less
useful Pakistan will eventually
disintegrate I hope it happens
peacefully I have no ill will towards
the people of Pakistan who have been
suffering since
1947 right so I have no ill will towards
the people of Pakistan but this is an
artificial temporary Nation its sole
purpose the the sole purpose for the
creation of Pakistan was to serve the
geopolitical interests of external
powers and not the interests of the
people so the sooner this happens the
better it
is okay now now let's take the big
question a lot of questions about this
matter which is this
Starling I have received a deluge of
questions about Starling so let's take a
look at a few of these questions Mr 88
says starlink has arrived in India is
our sovereignty doomed now Rohan says
starlink will now be available in India
is this the first step towards vasal
Hood Zeno zenth says has India already
become a US VI for allowing Geo and
Hertel to collaborate with starlink
kushbu says is India becoming a us vasal
the government has just bowed down to
allow allow Starling in India are we
slowly losing our sovereignty priyojit
mundel says as of now Gio and llink are
collaborating with starlink and be it's
going to be given access to India is it
going to be dangerous or has the Indian
government and a done some tweaks which
would save India's national security I
mean the starlink beam was already
facing India's Far East Northeast and
giving cookie separatist and terrorists
Intel from those satellites more
questions let's see some
more someone says before Tri made a
decision Ashwini ver of the the minister
of the government of India tweeted about
starlink coming to India and then
deleted it deleted the Tweet after a
backlash this raises concerns about
India's national sovereignty and
sensitive Technologies the involvement
of foreign um entities could lead to
data access in ways that are not fully
transparent as India moves towards the
visha guru
race could we be stepping into visha
something else opposed to visha Guru
risking strategic areas and high stakes
Technologies satendra says I've been
following okay thank you so much I
really appreciate that my question is
with reference to the article an article
published in the times of India the
title is Center sets tough question
tough conditions for India's entry by to
starlink will this move from the Indian
government as mentioned in this article
guarantee a protection from its
illegitimate use when it comes to access
of Starling services in disturbs
Disturbed areas like Manipur Northeast
India or a few parts of kmir I remember
you had ported out similar risk when it
comes to staring entering
India in various episodes and podcast
I've been doing that for quite some time
I have been saying for the longest time
Starling should not be allone in India
and I've I've I've given a list of
reasons why next question uh spy wolf
says as all the B audience knows and
understands SpaceX starlink is a threat
for India's security but recent news is
that go and Airtel have announced an
agreement with SpaceX for cheap
broadband internet now what's your views
on that illegal immigrants
imigrants
permission EVS now starlink what next
F35 let's take some more questions PR
Paul says Starling with Starling
partnering with bti AEL and Geo is India
strategically positioning itself in in
the global satellite internet race could
this move reshape India's digital
infrastructure while Al while also
raising concerns over for control of
critical communication networks how do
you see this move what difference does
it make having Airtel and goo on board
instead of letting starlink operate
independently as they do in other
countries is that the well thought out
strategy by the Indian government more
questions uh what's up with Starling now
is it over for us I'm 17 I only make two
prayers daily safety of my of my family
and prayers and progress of our country
is the L done for now I can't even
describe how low I am feeling right now
Indian stock picker says Starling
finally Finds Its way into India does
this partnership with goo and Airtel
make it anything different like data
sharing restrictions Etc how should we
see it from our country's defense and
geopolitical perspective Sid says it
looks like starlink has entered India
with these partnership what's my
opinions uh do you think this
partnership is to control what Starling
can do in India and they are not allowed
to operate independently but like a
joint venture on an Indian company and
lastly some more questions uh go
political du says there are media
reports that government of India
proposed Elon mus to establish darling
control room in India do you think it
will prevent the
dangers and Jason Grace says recently
yeah we know what's happened uh are we
Justified to feel concerned about the
supposed appeasement of trump in order
to Garner his favor is there some deeper
play going on which we might be missing
so many questions all valid questions
right
um so you may remember U there was this
episode on of ask abijit I think it was
Episode 229 in sometime in the end of
January which uh could be called the
wasal state episode in which in which I
was saying that we could be on our way
to becoming a us vate and you know it's
not so bad and all that and a lot of
people had said why are you being so
negative and all that people had people
lot of people were not happy about the
things I had said so here we are today
yeah starlink is entering India I have
been saying this for quite some time
starlink should not be allowed into
India for very clear
reasons very clear reasons let's say you
are a rioter and you are conducting
riots in some Indian city so typically
when this happens the government will
switch off mobile phone and internet
services in the region right but what if
there is star link available then the
riers can organize and do whatever they
want they can communicate as as per
their wishes and even if the government
switches off all local mobile and
internet internet services starlink will
still operate and then what can we do we
can shake our fist at the sky like Elon
Musk would say that's what the
government can do or let's say you are a
terrorist or or a
separatist a foreign infiltrator who has
crossed over from Burma into
Manipur and you are targeting civilians
and flying drones and bombing the city
the capital city with with drones right
and let's say the government is taking
action against these foreigners these
foreign barbaric
infiltrators and to do that the
government switches off mobile and
internet services but what if starlink
is available then these terrorists will
be able to operate with impunity and
project K will continue let's say you
were a Pakistani infiltrator into Jammu
and Kashmir into the Kashmir Valley and
there's this region in the Kashmir
Valley where there's no internet there's
no telephone services mobile phone
services but starlink is available I can
go on and on about these
scenarios
right and the fact that starlink is
operated by a foreign entity by Elon
Musk by the US means that they decide
when to turn it on and when to turn it
off and that's why starlink doesn't make
any sense for it doesn't make any sense
for us to have starlink India and that's
what I've been saying for quite some
time and uh my colleague Ram diedi also
has said the same thing and many other
sensible people are thinking this
Starling should not be allowed into
India it
will um you know compromise our
sovereignty and what is what do you call
a nation whose sovereignty is
compromised you call it a vasal state to
some extent not fully but to some extent
you know you when you're sovereign is
compromised you are not a fully
Sovereign Nation
right um so I will not comment about Mr
Ashwini vnav and him deleting the him
first tweeting a great warm welcome to
starlink and then deleting the Tweet
very quickly I will not comment about
that I will just make a note of that
this
happened um so now the first question
that arises is is what difference does
it make having Airtel and Geo
collaborating and partnering with
starling with Elon Musk instead of
letting starlink operate independently
like they do in other countries what
difference does it make so I'm not sure
what the modalities and parameters of
this of this uh uh collaboration are
like okay but starlink has is is is
going to collaborate with both these
companies so maybe it
means so how does Starling work they
have a constellation of satellites okay
let's look at zap of the planet and I'll
just give you an idea of how it
works um I want to show you the globe
not the map but the globe so here we
have the planet okay and you have a
constellation of satellites like
thousands of
satellites uh orbiting the Earth in
what's called reasonably low earth orbit
like 200 300 kilometers above the
surface of the planet okay and they keep
on orbiting all
across the surf all across the planet
thousands of satellites which means that
at any given point of time let's say
over India you will have a bunch of
satellites starting satellites that can
beam wireless internet to you okay now
so so that's basically how how starlink
works now you need a receiver obviously
right so starlink has these receivers
these are reasonably small devices that
you can put out maybe on your rooftop or
outside your window or in a balcony or
wherever and as long as there's a direct
line of sight with a satellite or a
bunch of satellites you will get a
reasonably low latency and reasonably
highp speed internet reasonably
right that's the deal so maybe the deal
is that Airtel and Gio May manufacture
those uh receivers
maybe that's the deal so if airel and
goo manufactured the receivers if if the
receivers Starling receivers are
manufactured in India maybe we can
install a kill switch in them which will
allow the government of India to um shut
off access switch off access so even if
the starlink uh beam or or signal is
being received the The Government Can
Tell Gio and airel to switch off access
in so and so area in so and so City or
Village or state or whatever maybe
that's the
deal okay so that so maybe having Airtel
and goo on board serves that
purpose so does it allow the government
of India to completely control
starlink and there's this report like
someone was saying that the center has
set tough conditions for India entry by
starlink I'm not sure what the tough
conditions are but uh if if go and
Airtel are manufacturing those receivers
then maybe it gives the government of
India
a some way of uh controlling access so
they can switch off uh the internet in
some areas but let's say you are a
cookie terrorist in Manipur and you have
brought in you have smuggled in uh
receivers from a different country let's
say you smuggled them in from Thailand
or wherever then you have a receiver
that's not manufactured by Goo rale then
then in that case you'll be able to
continue to receive the internet unless
Elon Musk himself switches it switches
it off over India well that's up to him
that's entirely up to him and we don't
control Elon
Musk right so that's the danger so maybe
Geo and AEL being um being on board
gives us a small amount of control over
starlink maybe there can be some data
sharing restrictions Maybe the
government can switch off internet in
various parts of the country as long as
the receivers are Geo or Airtel
receivers
right uh but it doesn't
completely doesn't give the government
complete control and maybe the starlink
beams are powerful enough that you can
access them directly on your
phones it's going to happen eventually
then you will not even need receivers
earlier you needed Uplink stations so in
in so the starlink satellite would
send a beam to an Uplink station or
something on the surface of the planet
and then the that Uplink station would
would serve would operate like a cell
phone tower and broadcast the the beam
all across the place now it's not not
needed anymore so you can directly
receive the signal on your receiver
probably eventually soon enough it will
be such that you can even without a
starling receiver you can directly get
it on on your cell phone or whatever
device in that case well there's no way
the government of India can control
starlink
right um so what's happening so the
question the big question everyone is
asking is are we becoming the V the
vasal a vasal of the
US
look we are
not we control our borders right that's
number one number two we control our
currency number three we pass our laws
we have complete complete control on the
laws and policies in the country right
so those things are there number four we
have complete control over our military
number five
um we have no foreign military bases on
our soil so these are the main hardcore
conditions for you to be a wasal of
another country so we don't have
that but
we are we we are essentially not
technologically
Sovereign we don't have technological
sovereignty in India technologically you
can perhaps say that we are a
technological vasal of the us we don't
have our own search engines we don't
have our own AI systems we don't have
satellite internet we don't have our own
Global
GPS we don't have our chip manufacturing
we we are in the process of setting it
up which will take a
while so technologically we are not
sovereign as a nation we are a
technological vasal of the west of the
us we are in that position
yes um yes so I would still say that
India is a Sovereign Nation India is not
a geopolitical vasal of the US like
Pakistan is or east Pakistan Bangladesh
is or the EU nations are
or Japan South Korea Etc are we are not
a vasal in that sense but
technologically we are super deficient
we have been very shortsighted
technologically and we are a
technological vasal of the
US so does does the entry of starlink
into India mean that uh we are appeasing
Donald Trump and we have uh yeah bu we
we have uh we have buckled and we are
appeasing Donald Trump yes it it does
mean
that make no mistake about it we are
giving Trump the wins that he
wants and at what I mean since we have
agreed to let this happen to have
Starling into India what are we getting
in exchange right now I mean there has
to be some give give or take give and
take right I give you this win what do
you give me an exchange I don't see any
any big win right now but but hold that
thought hold that
thought so ideally if you allow Starling
to come into India Elon Musk should have
set up some Tesla factories in India or
some giga factories or whatever nothing
of the sort he has not even bothered to
visit India that's that's a big big win
for them without getting anything in
exchange
right so look it's like this the US is a
super powerful Nation we are nothing
compared to the US if you have delusions
that India is a great near superpower
we're not
we are not even in the same league as
China or Russia not even close we are
the fourth most powerful nation in the
world which doesn't mean a big deal when
you're comparing yourself with the us so
you don't want to be on Trump's bad side
you want to give him the wins he
wants you give him the wins when it
comes to the Tariff issue okay you want
us to cut down the tariffs we'll cut
down the tariffs yes sir thank you sir
sorry we had kept the tariffs on now we
will cut everything down as as per your
wishes now number two starlink yes sir
starlink we'll have it we'll have it in
India yeah it is it it it is a big blow
to our technological sovereignty and
it's going to cause issues when it comes
to terrorism and infiltration and
separatism and riots and all that it
will cause issues okay
fine
but there is going to be a red line
somewhere the F35 now if we buy the F35
I'm going to say we are a full
vasal okay Trump wants us to buy the
F35 and a ridiculous piece of garbage
it's completely unsuitable for
India so if we buy that too that's
that's going to make me say that we are
genuinely in vasal territory now but I
think at some point in time we're going
to tell Mr Trump look Mr Trump we have
cooperated with you about this matter we
gave you all the wins you wanted on
tariffs we even allowed Starling to come
into India but there are certain things
that we we're going to have say no to
you sir and please understand we have
been extremely Cooperative but certain
things we're going to have to say no to
you about so the F35 hopefully is one of
those issues because that is going to
completely vassalize us the F35 and
also because we have given Trump these
wins it's going to come in handy in case
of future problems with China or other
nations so youve got to give the man
some wins in I mean I would wouldn't
have liked to see this happen starlink
coming into India but there we
are uh so yes it's definitely
appeasement of of of trump um defense
and and I mean all those perspectiv it's
it's bad for us you know what should
ideally have
happened what should have happened
ideally you
know goo or
Reliance should have set up their own
star link something like Geo link you
know uh Gio let's say Geo proposes to
the government of India that we going to
set up our own constellation of
satellites that will be a better
alternative cheaper faster Superior
alternative to Elon Musk Starling of
course we have the technology to do that
four five 6,000 satellites then Reliance
tells the government of India talk to
ISRO and we are giving them four or five
years to develop the technology of
reusable Rock reusable boosters so that
we can have one or two launches every
week it
took Space X between 2013 to 2016 2017
to completely perfect the uh you know re
reusable booster technology just four
years ISRO can do it in in less time and
make it even better we have the talent
in the in in the skills
so this would have turned ISRO into a
gigantic Beemo of global standards if
this had been proposed and agreed that
Gio launches geol link or Airtel
launches Airtel link which will out
compete starlink and we give is four
years to develop the technology and then
we start launching two two two rockets a
week with 100 satellites each we have
launched 100 plus satellites in the past
on the little pslb
so this could have been done it would
have transformed into India into a
genuine Global Behemoth Global Power
Player it would have given us Global
surveillance capabilities we would not
have needed uh so many things that we
need right now and we could even have
launched our own GPS kind of system with
this sort of Rocket launching
capabilities um but yeah we simply don't
have the vision of course it costs money
and all that but everything is feas
we have it's not like we don't have the
money in India so it's a huge
opportunity lost it is sad to
see um I had warned multiple times
against this and it's going to cause
challenges in India lots of security
challenges it's going to
uh cause challenges to over sovereignty
in the Border regions there is this
project K going on kiland for Christ
that will be that will receive a shot in
the arm once they start having U you
know internet in the in the in the
mountains and in the
forests so it's going to be a problem
but yeah that's where we stand
today I'm sorry I cannot give you a
better more more more a happier
interpretation of what's happening it is
what it is we are
technologically not a really Sovereign
Nation so technologically we are like 20
30 years behind the
world when we should not be we should
not have been there but that's where we
are okay next
question mclen says European nations are
concerned about the kill switch on the
F35 you've been talking about this for a
long time finally everyone is realizing
it now do you think they will cancel the
deal the European nations the deal of
the F35 of buying the F35 PR Paul says
with Germany now fearing a potential us
kill whichwich on its f35s amid growing
tensions with Washington what does this
signal for India as it reportedly uh
considers acquiring the same Jets uh you
have long warned about such risks citing
how the US can how the US once cut off
military technology to Australia one of
its closest allies given this precedent
could India face a similar vulnerability
how should India deal with this
essentially yes the infamous kill switch
when I spoke about the kill switch three
four years ago people were like what is
kill switch what is kill switch I've
never heard of kill switch today it's
mainstream yeah right here we are a kill
switch is a way of remotely disabling
military
technology like missile systems like
Radars like fighter jets like components
of fighter jets like drones uavs
whatever
right so I spoke I have spoken about
this multiple times in the 198 the
Americans sold F15 F5s to the
Australians and when the Australians got
the fighter jets new brand new fighter
jets and then took them out for a spin
to see what they can do they discovered
that the target acquisition system of
the f-15s would lock on only to targets
that the Americans had authorized they
would not lock on to practice targets or
any other targets like what then what's
the point of having this piece of
equipment
and it was not until the 20 2010s I
think that the Australians were finally
able to solve the problem and and crack
the
code so it was a piece of overpriced
garbage for the Australians if those
fighter planes refused to lock onto
targets that the Australians wanted them
to lock onto so the target acquisition
system and the radar was compromised by
the Americans to their closest allies
they did this you think they will give
you full control of the F35 if you buy
it yes
India India will not India will first of
all get an export variant of the f F35
which will be a much inferior version of
the play that the Americans and the
Israelis have and secondly every time
you want to fight every morning you're
going to have to get an OTP from the
Americans
okay and
then you will be allowed to lock onto
targets that they authorize only let's
say tomorrow morning for whatever reason
you you to do a strike on Pakistan it
won't be authorized it won't be allowed
then why do we need that piece of
garbage and do you know it is one of the
lowest serviceability rates in the world
the F35 for every hour it spends flying
you need to it has like 30 or 40 hours
it needs to be um
serviced because after every flight it's
radar coating the paint it it disappears
and you to paint the whole thing all
over again
so many issues that plane has and it's
so expensive to fly and you don't even
own it even if you have bought
it yeah so that's the kill switch that's
the kill switch it can be remotely
disabled um and anything that you buy
from the Americans can be remotely
disabled let's say you buy a missile
system that let's say airto a missiles
okay so your fight a plane with an
American missile on it and you want to
shoot down your enemy's figh a plane you
launch it and uh let's say it refuses to
lock onto the target what you going to
do what you going to do about it um
let's say you buy American uh drones you
know high altitude long endurance
drones okay these drones they rely on
GPS and so on which means they access
the
internet and they have chips and
whatever that comes from the US and
chips can have back doors and so on back
door if you don't know what a back door
is look it up so everything can be
compromised everything can be disabled
remotely and now the Germans have to
have sudden suddenly woken up to this
fact it's not like they didn't know
about this before but now they are
publicizing
it um so will the Europeans cancel the
F35 deal I don't know maybe they will
maybe they want what options do they
have do their are their fighter planes
all Sovereign
I mean for example if you uh let's let's
Google
this um us components
on European fighter planes like the
typhoon and whatnot Euro
Fighter so let's see this okay check
take take it take a look at this uh let
me remove the question okay European
fighter jets us
components uh so the the Swedish Sab
grippin um only a comparatively small
amount of the components and systems
found on the grippin are actually
designed and manufactured by Swedish
contractors okay a lot of it comes from
the US uh the G the general electric
engine and many other things then you
have yeah the grippin and the typhoon
Euro
Fighter so its engine is the UK's rolls
Roy the UK is America's number one vasal
so what do you expect and various other
us contract for the typhoon Euro Fighter
loid Martin Collins
Aerospace Honeyville Northrop griman and
so on then the dasal which is the most
indigenous of all the European planes
but even they have various us cont
contractors involved so the Americans
can you know if the Europeans act too
smart they can cut off access to various
things to the Europeans so my point is
even if the Europeans if the Europeans
try if they dare to cancel F35 orders
they'll suddenly find that all of their
military equipment expensive fighter
planes are suddenly useless they may
find
that okay um so that's a deal there's
nothing much the Europeans can do about
this all of their wonderful fighter
planes uh have a bunch large number of
American components and when you use the
US components you are always at the
mercy of the Americans and I'm not
saying it's a bad thing that the
Americans are doing doing they are doing
whatever it takes to further their
National interest as every nation should
do so it's just the way it is so what
should India do about this we should not
purchase the
F35 please I beg of the government of
India please don't purchase the
F35 moving charge with the magnetic
field says Russia is offering their Al
51 F1 Saturn engines the same that I
used in the suco 57 for the amca program
does it feel like a does it look like a
better engine than the General Electric
F
414 uh which we were initially thinking
of purchasing for the AMC considering
it's not a super Cruise uh enabled fight
uh jet engine and doesn't have thrust
vectoring so look there are the Saturn
engine it's a family of engines there is
the al31 there's the al-41 there's the
al-5 one the one that you talking about
is the al-51 F1 so the al31 is the
engine that is used in our suo the Su 30
mki we have a whole bunch of those in
India right big huge beasts of planes
with two uh Saturn al31 engines so the
Saturn al31 engine has about 76 kons of
dry thrust and more than 120 Kil of
thrust with afterburners wet thrust
that's the al31 that we use in our Su
then there's a better version of the of
that engine called the
al41 which is used in the sukko 35s and
also the Su
57 and it has its wet thrust After
Burner thrust is about 170 plus kilon
very powerful engine and then we have
the latest most advanced one al51 which
is still kind of under development it is
going to be used in the sukko 57 and in
the future
suco 75 which is still under development
so the al-51 has dry thrust of more than
100 Kil Newtons and with After Burner it
has a wdth Thrust of more than 160
almost 170
kons pretty powerful engine and it has
the thrust vectoring component you know
feature it can do thrust vectoring the
General Electric GF
414 it has dry thrust of less than 60
kons and its After Burner enabled wet
thrust is less than 100 kons so it's not
a very powerful engine there's no super
Cruise apparently I'm not sure and it
certainly doesn't have the thrust
vectoring capabilities that give fighter
planes super
maneuverability you know so any aircraft
that has the F f414 you'll find that it
cannot do the pugachev Cobra maneuver
the Cobra
maneuver but the so 57 good God the
things it does H um so so it's clear
that the uh Al 51 Saturn latest one is
far superior to the American
f414 and when it comes to buying
American components there's there's
always issues okay they can deny
technology they can switch components
turn components disable components off
and so on I'm not sure if you can
disable components remotely in a jet
engine but who knows you better be
careful we have been Russ using Russian
engines and components for so long we
have never had these
issues we've had some other issues
that's a whole different story but not
they've never tried to deny us
technology deny us
um the use of what we have purchased and
they've never ever remotely disabled
anything right so I would say we should
go for the al51 F1 or whichever engine
they're giving we don't need an engine
that is the best in the world we need an
engine that's just good
enough the the question really is are
they offering what are they offering the
Russians are they giving us a license to
assemble engines in India in in which
case I have I don't
care what I would want is the full
technology so that we can on our own
manufacture these engines in India with
Indian components with Indian materials
without having to import this component
or that part from
Russia or or importing spare parts from
Russia nothing from Russia we
manufacture everything in India with our
own materials that is called Full
transfer of Technology are they offering
us
that if they are offering us that then
we should close our eyes and buy it
whatever be the
price but I'm not sure if they're
offering us that right so it depends on
various things if if that engine is
being offered to us with full
technological transfer then we should
certainly go with go for it with our
eyes closed it's definitely a great
engine I think the al-51 is still under
development but the al-41 is a great
it's it's a great
engine so yeah if you're getting one of
these engines just go for it buy it and
in the meanwhile keep developing the C
engine Abhijit chavda light says at this
time what should be beneficial for
Ukraine what's the best action they can
take to protect their
country good question look let's think
of think about this unemotionally and
logically
Ukraine is
currently fighting a war against
Russia right special military operation
whatever you want to call it and Russia
currently controls roughly 20% of
Ukraine Ukraine's territory which means
Ukraine has lost sovereignty over about
20% of its territory roughly give or
take and this war has has been going on
since February late February
2022 it's been more than three years now
Ukraine's economy has been devastated
Ukraine's demographics have been Dev
devastated Ukraine has lost hundreds of
thousands of lives soldiers on the front
lines right disaster absolute disaster
for the country so what are the options
Ukraine has look there are two options
option
one fight the war and defeat Russia
completely you get
it option one is to somehow achieve a
military victory over Russia and regain
all the
territory and Achieve whatever political
gains you have so option one is a
military victory over
Russia and option two is an immediate
end to the war so that there is no
further loss of life lives and what
whatnot so if it is possible defeat
Russia
militarily is option one of complete
military defeat of Russia
possible have you seen any sign of that
in the past three
years no right even with hundred
hundreds of billions of
dollars of aid from the US
Ukraine still is in a situation today
after three years where it has lost at
least about 20% of its territory and
it's it's on its
knees right I think nobody can deny
today that Ukraine is on its knees today
and it's not winning this war and even
if the Americans send another $500
billion do of Aid Ukraine still can't
defeat Russia because it's already used
up about 500 billion or 350 billion
whatever and there's no more ammunition
arms left in the west to keep feeding
Ukraine Germany France EU NATO what will
they do they're not in a situation
they're not in a position to keep
supplying Ukraine with an endless amount
of arms and ammunition they don't have
the factories they don't have all of
that and the US has lost patience now
how much more money do we sync in this
matter so it's clear Ukraine cannot
defeat Russia militarily if you maybe
they can continue the war another three
years which means Ukraine will be
completely devastated nothing will be
left so option one a military defeat of
Russia is impossible so what is the
better option now it's an immediate
ceasefire and an immediate end to this
madness that is the only thing that's
beneficial to Ukraine how many more
lives do you people want to
lose you have no young men left
so I think the best course of action is
an immediate
ceasefire Putin doesn't have super
unreasonable terms he will retain the
territory he has already taken and he
wants Ukraine should never join
NATO and so on so
forth agree to the terms and end the war
immediately that's the best course of
action for
Ukraine okay another question by AB out
the light if European countries are not
sovereign then why are they disagreeing
with Trump's peace peace peace deal in
the Ukraine
war that's a great question isn't it so
why are the European nations not
sovereign am I have I lost my mind when
I said that the European nations EU
nations are not
sovereign some people will ask has
abijit chaa lost his mind he's claiming
the EU nations are not sovereign Nations
what is talking about
ha what does it mean to be a Sovereign
Nation first of all a Sovereign Nation
first of all has complete control over
its
borders it can decide who comes in and
who doesn't come
in it it can decide who can immigrate
and who can who is not allowed to
immigrate none of the EU Nations has any
control over its border over their
borders there goes one piece of your
sovereignty secondly to be a Sovereign
Nation you need to have complete control
over your laws and your policies and the
policies that you implement you decide
what laws are going to be framed what
laws will be enforced and what policies
will be enforced your people have
complete ownership over that in the EU
none of the EU
Nations frame their laws the laws come
from Brussels the policies come from
Brussels they're dictated to the nations
from Brussels so that's another piece of
your sovereignty gone number three a
sovereign nation has complete control
over its economy which means it's
currency its own currency it should have
its own currency in the EU none of the
Nations has its own
currency there a common currency called
the Euro which is a rebranded D
mark that's another piece of your
sovereignty gone and then for a nation
to be Sovereign you need to have
complete control over your military and
none of the EU Nations even has
that because most of the EU nations are
part of
NATO NATO and in NATO you have control
over your
military so none of the EU nations are
sovereign Nations and if they're also
member of NATO they are even less
Sovereign and then in Sovereign na in a
Sovereign Nation you have rulers or
leaders who represent the people in the
EU Nations you have bureaucrats who
masquerade as leaders and they serve
Brussels they don't represent their
people and they don't serve their
people and all these EU nations are
police states where the police doesn't
Serve and Protect the people
it enforces the r of the bureaucrats who
rule over the
people
okay so that's the de that's why the
European countries are not
sovereign so if they are not sovereign
why are they disagreeing with Trump who
is the president of the US the big
Master the big the over Overlord of
Europe because since 1945 there's only
been one power in Western Europe which
is the US right the US is the puppet
master that controls NATO as well as the
EU and the president is Trump so why are
they disagreeing with Trump right that's
the
question see Trump wants to completely
reshape the global order and the
geopolitical balance of power um for the
for the longest time since 1945 the EU
Nations European nations Western
European nations have been treated like
royalty they've been given all these
Sops and all these
subsidies because of which they have
turned been turned into into welfare
states they don't pay for their military
expenditure they don't pay for defense
there so much that is subsidized by the
US and Trump wants to end all that so
that obviously will be very shaky for
Europe and it will completely shake up
these people's hold over power these
little bureaucrats who rule the EU
Nations they are
frightened and they are members of the
Ona regime the old regime which was
all run by the Democrats right if you
look at the US establishment the
so-called superficial deep State all the
bureaucrats who run the show they're
all left leaning people they're all
they're all people who vote for the
Democrats and all so a lot of these EU
leaders all these people they are very
strongly align with the American
Democratic party not the Republican
party they don't like the Republicans
that's another reason why they don't
like Trump so because of this there is
this big um there is this uh big refusal
right now there's this big resistance in
the EU towards what Trump wants to do
and that's why they are disagreeing with
Trump's peace deal and they want the war
in Ukraine to keep on going and it's
possible that they must be getting some
benefit from the war in Ukraine Maybe
see the Americans have spent about 350
or maybe 400 maybe 500 billion dollars
in in the war effort in Ukraine maybe
they are getting some of that maybe
they're getting a cut it's possible it's
corruption you know the United
Nations this organization that is
supposed to maintain peace in the world
and they have peacekeeping operations
and all and they've got this huge budget
in the UN right and you know how this
budget is used a very large portion of
the United Nations budget is used for
business class travel and festar hotel
stays of their bureaucrats and employees
all the money is much of the money is
wasted allegedly in this manner this is
called
corruption the EU is also allegedly
super corrupt like this so all these
people this they are self-serving people
they are all they have this big network
of people who are all useless who don't
serve the people they're all
self-serving people and they want to
maintain their hold over power and
that's why they are disagreeing with
Trump's peace deal and opposing
Trump this is Harsh kapor says in
Germany the CDU party has won the
election they came out of statement that
they'll withdraw from NATO haha and
eventually they will do away with
American tyranny Germany doing away with
American
tyranny hypothetically if Germany does
step back then what implications can it
face economically from the US how will
the US how will India be impacted Etc uh
how will Putin react to this if it
happens anytime soon does Germany have
the potential to capture the whole of
Europe except France and handshake with
France and Russia eventually does this
mean kicking America's backside and
cutting America's access from
Europe
okay to cut off America's access from
heral Germany would need to take over
militarily all of
okay for that you need a gigantic
military
machine you need thousands of Tanks
thousands of
aircraft millions of troops you need a
you need a war
economy does Germany have a war
economy right now there are companies
like uh I don't know which
company Volkswagen are saying that we
have some unused factories that we are
man that were manufacturing cars we can
manufacture tanks in
that Volkswagen manufacturing
tanks it kind of brings back memories of
the Third Reich doesn't it Germany
doesn't have a v economy Germany is
almost in recession it was in recession
some time ago it may be out of it now
but it's not doing well economically and
and for a war effort you need a great
amount of energy fuel
where's the fuel going to come from will
Vladimir Putin help them with fuel
northstream 2 northstream three
whatever Germany doesn't have the
capability doesn't have the capacity to
do any of this it's all talk talk talk
it's all words no there's no potential
there's no capacity for
action it's all words big
words um so they they don't have the cap
capability to do do any of these things
uh and if if they if they you know try
to withdraw from n NATO the Americans
won't allow
it and uh they'll make life very very
hard for the Germans and then there's
also the issue that Germany is crippled
internally right there got millions of
horrific
immigrants the kind of immigrants no
Nation should should allow those have
been brought into Germany the there's
all this Strife within the nation and so
on Germany is on is not on on strong
ground unfortunately it's it's been it's
been weakened greatly it doesn't
have an army to to speak of they have
the L which is just symbolic which is
their Air Force and so on they have
American troops on their
soil the Americans control
everything uh there's not much the
Germans can do Beyond talk talk talk so
it's not going to happen unfortunately
for them and I think lots of Nations
will say thank God it can't happen
they've already seen Germany rise in
that manner before during the age of the
painter and they would be very scared to
see that happen again so yeah I don't
think it's possible for Germany to do
that even if they wanted to and lastly
for for any of this to happen you need
an exceptional
leader there are no exceptional or even
decent leaders in Germany
that it's it's just not there the
political system is such that only
corrupt little petty little people can
rise to the top little little guys
little
bureaucrats I mean look at the past five
chancellors they've had who of them was
a person of substance you're going to
say Angela Merkel was a lady of
substance or leader of substance she's
the one who brought in this this
huge influx of illegal immigrants into
Germany
people you know military age men from
certain
countries whose cultural values are
completely at at odds with German German
culture she's the one who did this to
Germany would you call her a person of
substance a leader of substance and so
on so forth so Germany doesn't produce
great leaders anymore the system ensures
that no great leader is
produced so it's not going to
happen Sun Moon uh 0877 says is the US
going through a massive hyperinflation
just like Russia faced during the 1990s
after the dissolution of the USSR why is
Trump following Russia's footsteps will
the US have a dictator soon so I'm not
sure why you feel that there is
hyperinflation in the US hyperinflation
means like runaway inflation not 3% 5%
it's like 300% or 500% or 3,000% that's
called hyperinflation so let's look at
the kind of INF inflation Russia had in
the 1990s let me put this uh page on the
screen and let's compare do a
comparative analysis so this is the
hyperinflation in Russia the
1990s in the year
1993 uh
943 per inflation 943 37% 95 2
36% then 96
51% then
at the turn of the century you again had
58% 46% and so on so yeah you had so
these these figures represent
hyperinflation more than 100% inflation
that's kind of hyperinflation obviously
you I can give you examples of even
worse hyperinflation but you get the
point this is what hyperinflation looks
like ridiculous inflation figures now
let's take a look at what kind of
inflation we have in the US today shall
we okay current US inflation rates
between 2000 and
2025 so let's see the inflation 2017 2.1
2018 1.9 uh 2021 7% inflation then 6.5%
inflation during the covid era and now
it's 3.4 2.9 and this year it's 2.8%
inflation in the US today so where is
the hyperinflation you you get the point
so this is not hyperinflation this is
just regular inflation and it's
definitely not out of
control so as you can see from those
figures there is no hyperinflation
massive hyperinflation in the US
absolutely not
whatsoever so Trump is not following in
any Russian footsteps there is no
hyperinflation I'm not sure where you
get this idea from but once you see
those numbers those figures you'll see
that it's not the case will the US have
a dictator soon that's an interesting
question you know people have been
trying to portray Trump as a dictator
from the day he became president the
first time 2016 oh he he has got
dictatorial Tendencies and so on so
forth the US will not have a dictator no
US president will be allowed to become a
dictator any US president who tries to
become a little more powerful than he's
allowed
to that person gets
1963 what happened in the year 1963
let's let's find out shall we um
uh what happened in
1963 1963 what
[Music]
happened
ah
um the assassination of President
Kennedy right was it
1963 it was 1963 there you have it my
point is any US president who tries to
go against
uh The
Establishment is going to be in danger
of being
1963 and to be a dictator you have to go
against the establishment and take power
for yourself not going to
happen because the US is run by the Deep
State the actual deep State not the
bureaucracy something even
deeper and one if you want to see a
symptom of the deep State real
symptom you have to look at the US
Federal Reserve it's like in India we
have the Reserve Bank of India right
which controls the overall economy in
the US you have the Federal Reserve Bank
now in India The Reserve Bank of India
is owned by the by the government of
India it comes under the government of
India it's controlled by the by the
government of India by the finance
ministry in the US the Federal Reserve
Bank is a private
bank it is not under the control of the
US president
and its
shareholders are not known we don't know
who owns this Bank you not allowed to
know who owns this bank so it's it's the
other way around in the US the Federal
Reserve owns the US
economy the government of government of
the US doesn't own the economy there you
have a real symptom of the deep state so
the US is a dictatorship it's a nation
that's owned by a bunch of people but we
don't quite know who they
are interesting you think it's a
conspiracy theory go look
up the Federal Reserve Bank who owns it
shall we shall let's let's do it because
why
not who owns the FED Federal
Reserve is not owned by anyone it's a
public agency it's okay it's not a
private entity apparently Who are the
who are are the uh shareholders of the
Federal
Reserve um not owned by anyone blah blah
okay you will never get an answer okay
you will never get an
answer interesting Nation this the
United
States okay Sam Satish says there's news
about shikina that that she will return
to Bangladesh
Trump in his meeting with Modi G also
mentioned that bhat is free to take care
of the situation in Bangladesh if shik
kazen had to return to Bangladesh after
all this why would the US Place Muhammad
yunus the great Noble Laureate there
what do you think is the future of
Bangladesh um so there's this you know
Indian news channels and Indian news
anchors they have taken this statement
from Trump and flown with it Trump has
had said during his press
meeting with Prime Minister Modi when
asked about Bangladesh he said Trump
said I will leave Bangladesh to Mr Modi
to Prime Minister Modi what Trump was
doing he was deflecting the question
from the reporter he did not want to
answer the question about Bangladesh so
he just said I will leave Bangladesh to
PM Modi and then the Indian news readers
and anchors took that statement and told
the Indian public that Trump is now
giving Bangladesh back to
India that is such a
reible
reible interpretation such an asinine
interpretation the US is not going to
give up its
asset they have two assets on two sides
of India in the East and the west east
Pakistan and West Pakistan why would
they give it up why give up your
leverage over a nation like India
they'll not do it sh Casina is not going
to Bangladesh she's not not going to
return
and if she does she's not going to be
able to influence politics in any way
whatsoever if she does return I don't
see that happening if I am wrong and if
she does return even then she'll not be
able to participate in politics in any
meaningful
way um so yeah the US is not giving up
its leverage over India in the form of
this wasal state Bangladesh not going to
happen Okay unknown real says I'm a
lower middle class Hindu and a first
year student from Bangladesh my question
is after graduation should I move to
India or should I convert to Islam which
I don't want to do reason in Bangladesh
after H left the situation for Hindus
was similar to that of the alawites in
Syria for a few months yeah what's
happening in Syria right now to the
alites we know now the situation feels
like Pakistan however nothing about this
is shown on the news channels or social
media because we receive death threats
with such security concerns it doesn't
seem possible to stay in Bangladesh
that's why I want to move to India but
after observing India's various politics
and secularism I feel that Hindus are
the only enemies of Hindus in India so I
want to know what should I
do yeah first of all uh there is this
tremendous persecution of Hindus that's
happening in Bangladesh and and the
media doesn't report it social media
stays quiet about this yeah we know that
um what should be done and look so you
so you have two options right um you
want
to you don't want to convert to Islam
you will be yeah under under pressure to
do that uh so then you have two options
you either move to
India or what else in India you will
find my dear friend sadly that Hindus
are second class citizens okay India is
the world's world's most hinduphobic
Nation Hindus have more rights in the US
us and in the west than in
India the Constitution itself
discriminates against Hindus so if you
want to have full religious freedom as a
Hindu and if you want to be able to
breathe freely for the first time in
your life I would
say go go and move to the West it's so
sad and so strange to give you such
advice but yeah if you genuinely want
full religious
freedom and and be an equal citizen like
with everybody else I think moving to
the West is is a good option in India
Hindus are second class citizens so yeah
it's it's I'm I'm glad you are bringing
this up that there's so much persecution
happening in Bangladesh against Hindus
and the media doesn't report it doesn't
cover
it so thank you for bringing for raising
this issue over here and I would suggest
that if and when possible as soon as
possible move the West that's where
you'll be able to practice U your
religious freedom to the
fullest pray Paul says China's Embassy
in the US has issued a bold statement if
war is what the US wants be let it be a
tariff war or trade war or any other
type of War we are ready to fight till
the end is this just rhetoric or or does
China actually have the capability and
strategic positioning to back up such a
challenge how serious serously should
the US and its allies take this I think
the US and its allies should take this
very
seriously the Chinese have the world's
biggest Navy in terms of numbers and
they warships are increasingly more
sophisticated the Chinese are
technologically almost as advanced now
as the US the Americans tried to impose
chip sanctions on the on the Chinese
conductor sanctions the Chinese have
just produced their own technology now
they can make chips of any size whatever
Dimensions it is the Chinese have almost
caught up with the
US even without the photo lithographic
machines that uh that asml manufactures
even without that the Chinese have been
able to catch up with the US in the in
terms of EVS Etc the Chinese are ahead
of the US in terms when when it comes to
stealth technology fighter planes and
all that the Chinese are almost right up
there with the US when it comes to drone
technology the Chinese are right up
there or maybe even ahead of the US
ahead when it comes to AI the Chinese
seem to be perhaps at least in public
ahead of the
US so the
Chinese and the Chinese have the economy
the big the second biggest largest
economy in the world right so so yeah
the US will take this very seriously you
may
remember from 2007 or 8 onwards 2012
onwards the Chinese entered this phase
that we call Wolf Warrior diplomacy
their Diplomat suddenly became super
ultra
aggressive issuing threats against
everybody all over the place super
aggressive diplomats and this was called
wolf Warrior diplomacy and you may not
have noticed that ever since covid
started 2019 2020 thereabouts wolf
Warrior diplomacy suddenly
disappeared and the Chinese have been
very quiet since
then they have been hiding their
strength like then shopping would say
they've suddenly realized around that
that time they realized we need to just
keep quiet keep a low profile once
again so since covid happened the
Chinese have kept a very low profile
they've stopped making threats they've
stopped pushing people around they've
been very quiet and now at this juncture
if they issue this this statement that
we are ready for any kind of War I think
the Americans need to take it very
seriously geopolitical dub says can his
Holiness the Dal Lama successor be
non-chinese and what if his Holiness
doesn't announce his successor in his
lifetime the Dalai Lama successor has to
be non-chinese
the Dal Lama his successor has to be
Tibetan
right so obviously it's going to be
non-chinese
uh so that's very clear that the Lama's
successor will be Tibetan not
Chinese now what if his Holiness the
Lama doesn't doesn't
announce doesn't clarify the issue of
his succession in his lifetime what
happens then so what's the issue of the
theama succession so generally when the
L passes
away it is said that his a his soul will
reincarnate within a few years in a
child
inet and so the monks they look for a
set of
signs which will be associated with the
birth of the new Dal Lama and that's how
they identify the child who is The
Reincarnation of the Dal Lama okay
that's I'm saying this in very
brief now the present Dal Lama is quite
elderly
I hope he lives beyond 100 I hope so but
eventually he's going to have to leave
his body right he's going to have to
pass on so then the question is what
happens
then the Chinese government would very
much like to control the process of the
appointment of the next dalil
Lama so if the Pres the current dalil
Lama doesn't clarify the issue of his
succession and he passes away excuse me
without doing that then the Chinese
government will take control of the
matter and they will appoint their own
Dal Lama in Lassa who's going to be a
Chinese Communist party controlled Dal
Lama um so they will take ownership of
the institution of the Dal Lama they
will take ownership of it right now the
institution of Dal Lama is is not owned
by the Chinese government it operates
out of India
dhamala so ideally what his Holiness
should do is he should make a clear
unambiguous Declaration of how the suc
the issue of the succession should be
handled he should make it very clear
where he intends to reincarnate if he
does intend to reincarnate maybe he can
say that I this this life time will be
my last last Lifetime and I will not
reincarnate anymore I will go and attain
Nirvana so there will be no more theas
after me he can he can make the
statement if he does make that statement
then anything the Chinese government
tries after this will be automatically
null and Vo
because has said that I will not
reincarnate otherwise if he does intend
to reincarnate after he passes on then
he can make a clear statement that I in
my next birth will be born in so and so
place maybe not in Tibet maybe I'll be
born in India or maybe I'll be I'll take
birth among the Tibetan diaspora outside
of Tibet or whatever he wishes so he
needs to clarify the matter once and for
all and if it doesn't do that then the
Chinese government will take control of
the
institution so let's see how it
goes h of warrior says after the recent
Champions Trophy win by the Indian team
I can see a lot of Articles from various
foreign news outlets pitting Venom lots
of ifs ifs and buts on their in the
Articles portraying India's Victory as a
hollow win favoritism unfair politics in
was BBC with ultra all that stuff what's
my take on
this keep on whining losers India won
yeah look India got you can say some
some amount of preferential treatment
all the teams had to travel to various
cities to play their matches and India
India played all its matches out of one
location which was Dubai and obviously
we will not go in soverign Pakistan
because it's a terrorist nation and our
the safety of of our team is not
guaranteed in Pakistan so we decided to
play our matches out of
Dubai it is what it is um so some people
will claim that yeah India got
preferential treatment because India is
the richest cricketing nation the BCCI
is the most powerful and the richest
board and so on let them make these
claims in the past it was very different
in the past it was the the English the
Australians who used to run the roost
who used to rule the roost and do
whatever the hell they felt
like okay with money comes the you get
this perks and India has not been an
unfair Nation okay India has not been
misusing its its power and its clout
there are very weak teams that would not
survive if India if India did not tour
them India even tours Zimbabwe when was
the last time Australia or England
toured Zimbabwe India tours Zimbabwe
from time to time maybe in od series or
T20 series or whatever we even tour
Zimbabwe the West Indies used to be one
of the greatest teams of all time the
most powerful team in the world today
they are a very weak team unfortunately
it's sad to say that but India every
year or every couple of years sends a
team on a tour to the West Indies to
ensure that the West Indies uh board
has a flow of Revenue and so on India
has been very fair to everybody and yet
the BBC and these the some of these
people they just they jealous of India's
success I'll tell you how the
Australians to do things okay uh let me
search 1994 Australia Tri series okay
1994 Australia Tri series let's let's
let's search for this together shall
we
1994 Australia Tri series let's let's
search for
this uh 9495 Australia Tri series try
Nation
series I think this
one so this was the Australians usually
have a triangular tournament every year
in Australia it used to be called the
Benson and the hedges World Series in
the early '90s and then the tri
series The 9495 Tri series wasn't was
not a tri series The Australians played
two
teams Australia and Australia a and the
other two teams were England and
Zimbabwe can you believe the Australians
decided that they will play two
teams internationally they deployed two
teams Australia a and Australia in an
International
Tournament if India did that today you
can imagine the kind of criticism we
would cop but the Australians and the
English could get away with any kind of
nonsense they
wanted before the IPL India did not have
any power so you know what I would say
see India has the kind of depth that no
no nation has India can deploy a
separate test team separate one day team
separate T20 Team India can deploy two
separate test teams two separate one day
teams two separate T20 teams
maybe India should take a fiveyear break
from international cricket and turn the
IPL into a year round tournament like
eight nine months like the football
leagues in Europe and have an IPL for
t20s have an IPL for for for Odis and I
have an IPL for
tests and we have such vast reservoir of
of players we can keep this going and we
can bring in the world's best talent by
giving
them the high salaries that they that
everybody hopefully
deserves if India does that it's going
to end Cricket globally but India
doesn't do that India is a responsible
nation and people are jealous of India
and that's why you will see all of this
I mean one of the Great West Indies fast
Bowlers Andy Roberts one of the great
Bowlers you know he has criticized
India when it comes to the Champions
Trophy win these people
I mean Andy Roberts you're a black man
your people were oppressed and enslaved
by by the anglos and now you are coming
up coming in and and criticizing India
in defense of your Earth while
oppressors come on man sad to see this
so my point is it is jealousy it's
bitterness that the Earth while
colonized are now the colonizers so be
it
VII Manar says I'm extreme okay two
questions I'm extremely saturated
working in anti-india snake pits and I
don't have any the capacity anymore what
should I do should I mentally give up on
bhat because it's all messed up and even
the system is totally self-sabotaging
what should I do I feel broken and
helpless from inside so I don't know
where you work if you're working in an
anti- India snake pit maybe I don't know
I I have no idea where it work so I
can't I can't say based on that uh but
yeah
um if you're feeling frustrated if
you're feeling burnt out if you're
feeling all that then for the sake of
your own well-being mental well-being
and all you need to step away from
that uh should you give up on bat no you
should not give up on bat why do you
need to give up on bat bat isn't the
problem the corrupt system the corrupt
parasitic system that is sucking away
the life blood of India that is the
problem the corrupt system is the
problem bat is not the problem
so you don't have to mentally give up on
bat bat will eventually be fine we are
going through this phase and these
phases they last decades sometime
centuries we are going through this
phase right now eventually we
will come back on top um so it's a game
of patience our patience need to needs
to extend to centuries you don't have to
mentally give up on bat but if you are
trapped in a system that is so which
which you can't take anymore
you need to step out of it and and
dissociate yourself from it and go
somewhere else somewhere better if you
have to leave the country and work
somewhere else so be it but you should
not give up on parat mentally you still
should love your
country okay yeah there are so many
people who have bad experiences working
in India and they start hating India as
a result India isn't the problem it is
this corrupt mediocre people and the
corrupt and mediocre system that is is
the problem and this system pushes up
all the wrong people to the top and then
you feel that the whole of the country
is is like this and the country doesn't
deserve my love which is not the case
Okay so if you feel helpless if you feel
broken from inside if you can't stand
the system anymore please move out of
the
system and and yeah do whatever is best
for you as an individual and maybe for
your family that's what I would say uh
the second thing is you only take
questions from comments that feel like
you're to your own
self there was a time when he would also
take questions from the live chat and
that was really fun and interactive uh
the world is already irritating I hope
at least this show will retain its
Essence well VII G if you see episode
one of ask abijit you will see that I
took questions from the comments if you
see episode two I took questions from
the comments if you see the first 10
episodes I mainly took questions from
the comments if you see the first 100
epis episodes at least 70 80% of the
episodes I took questions from the
comments the essence of this show is
mainly taking questions from the
comments because that way I can select
the best possible questions that will
give the best value to the
audience but yes I I do hear what you
are saying and of late I am almost not
taking any questions at all from the
live chat so maybe I can mix and match
things a little bit maybe once in a
month in a month month you have
generally four weeks maybe in a month at
least one episode I can do which is full
live chat yeah so I hear you and I will
mix it up and let's say the next week's
episode will be only live chat how about
that okay it'll be very interactive so
yeah I I make this commitment right now
next weekend's episode we I will take
questions only from the live chat you
know
what it is so easy for me to take just
questions from the live chat I don't
have to do any work at all if I take
questions from the comments I have to go
through hundreds of comments read them
all then select the best questions it's
so much time that I have to spend so
much work I have to do if I don't take
questions from the comments and just do
live chat it's it's so easy for me it's
easier that way so I'm actually putting
in so much more work to take the best
questions but okay uh next weekend I
will take questions only from the live
chat no comments how about that all
right shagun Chopra says uh can you
please tell me how to deal with toxic
people at the workplace I mean sometimes
ignoring this isn't
possible
e okay I I I get it
look
um toxic people are everywhere
especially in some fields and some
organizations and so on toxic people you
will find everywhere so how do you deal
with
them it's a there are multiple ways you
can deal with them the first thing is
you move somewhere else I mean see in an
organization you have this ladder right
the corporate ladder and the people who
perform better they usually move up the
ladder and the people who are toxic and
useless they stay be stay down so one
way of moving uh dealing with them is to
outperform them and out promote them
mean which means you Pro you get you get
promoted and they stay behind but
sometimes you have toxic bosses what to
do
then in that case look if you are stuck
with a toxic boss I would say that the
best thing is to move to a different
place different
organization uh but typically every
organization has a certain number of
toxic people and it's like that um so
what do you do you if you are in an
environment where you have toxic people
and there's no way of removing yourself
from them then you have to somehow
harden yourself you know develop a
thicker skin and learn the art of verbal
and other self-defense against toxic
people you know don't give them control
and power over you push back learn
verbal self-defense learn whatever
tactics are required to prevent that
toxicity from uh hurting you uh so um
and and how to do all that it's it's a
whole thing in itself so yeah there are
two three things you can do one is to
move out second is to outperform them so
that you go above them and third thing
if you simply can't escape them then you
to develop various self-de defense
mechanisms like learning what to say how
to
say and develop a thicker skin all of
that so yeah multiple things you can do
I don't know the exact circumstances
that you are in so I can't give you any
specifics but uh the best possible thing
is
to is to remove yourself from such an
environment and find a better place to
work in if it's possible at all so ma'am
all the best I'm sorry that you are in
this situation but uh yeah hopefully
things work out for
you prakar Gupta says why is reading
history important most people ignore re
reading history and they say it's
useless why read history what's the
point why read stuff that happened in
the past so boring all that stuff right
that's what most people say look reading
history is very important you don't know
what's happening imagine you you you are
a voter in an election and you have
let's say five candidates from five
different political parties
and you have no idea about the history
of this person and the history of their
political party then how will you decide
who to vote for you have no idea what
this person represents what this this
person stands for what this person's
track record is like and what the
political party's ideology track record
and past performance is
like then how will you vote you will
basically try and see who who looks the
best to me who is the most popular who
speaks the best who gives me the best
Vibes is that how you vote no you don't
vote like that you need to know
everything about the person in the
political party and what they stand for
and what they've done in the past what
the track record is so that's why you
need to learn hist one re that's one
reason
right by studying history you are able
to comprehend comprehend the factors
that have shaped the world reading
history helps us
understand why this the world exists in
the current shape and form it helps us
understand where we are today and why we
are here today and why it is the world
is the way it is right it helps us
understand what are the factors and what
are the things things the forces that
shape the
world studying history helps us
understand change how does change happen
why does change happen what are the
factors that affect change that cause
change why do some societies Thrive why
do some societies crumble why do this
they fall why do Empires rise and fall
why do why do cultures rise and fall why
do humans go to war why do Nations and
societies and kingdoms and Empires go to
war
how do people change society for the
better and what kind of people destroy
Society right if you study history you
can learn from past mistakes so that you
don't make mistakes again studying
history by studying history you
understand human psychology you
understand the past you understand the
cycles and the trends that happen over
and over again that way you can predict
future Trends you understand cause and
effect causality the causal chain
right by studying history you can learn
from the past and by studying history
you can notice warning
science by studying history you can
understand your culture your
civilization you understand the
strengths and weaknesses of your
nation you understand who you are you
understand your identity and you
understand who your enemies are by
studying history you can learn decision
making and problem solving it's so much
more so these are some of the reasons
why you should learn
history but yeah history can be history
the way it is taught it's extremely
boring which is why I understand by
people don't like reading history but
yeah you got to learn it you got to
study
it so chakra says I understand that
Scholars and others say Afghanistan
wasn't part of the Indian civilization I
don't understand that it was but okay um
but rather belong to the Iranian World
okay however why is kutan considered to
be Iranian and part of the Iranian World
instead of the Indian civilization by
Scholars is it fair to give everything
of Indian to the Iranians what are your
thoughts on this okay let's go to the
map where is
kotan
Ghana MH Gana okay so here we are it's a
India is Right bang in the center let's
go north of
India let's go north of ladak and you
see something called hotan
prefecture okay let's zoom in this is
historical
kotan the terrain is very much like what
you find in
ladak now if you read if you study the
history of
hotan uh k h o t n you will find that it
was originally called Gana g s t h Gana
and it was founded by in indan Travelers
during the morian era during the time of
the morian Empire the time of Emperor
Ashok and his successors around that
time that's when kotan was
founded um so it's clearly something
that was founded by
Indians uh but yeah you you will have
you know historians and Scholars who
will say that uh it's
Iranian so you will find this this
tendency among uh all these Scholars and
historians to try and make everything
Indian
Iranian first of all this name Iran it's
a modern name the name Iran came up in
the early 20th
century and it was Iran was always
called
Persia for thousands of years since
about 1,000 BC roughly it was called
Persia the Persian people were the
descendants of the parwa clan of Vic
Indians parha their Capital was called
parur persopolis the Greeks called it
persopolis the origins of Persia
themselves are
Indian but people try to
retrofit
everything you know whatever you see
today you try to fit fit it
backwards you try to superimpose to
today's worldview and
today's whatever is happening in the
world on the past so if you look at
Persia
today it's not very Persian at least
about half of the people of Persia are
not Persian
today there are so many people in Persia
who look like Europeans right they got
blonde hair and blue eyes and white skin
the real Persians look like this like
this light brown skin brown brown brown
eyes and dark hair I don't have dark
hair anymore but you get the point this
is what persans look like historically
their kings wor dois do you know
that don't believe me I I'll pull out a
okay I don't have the time to show that
but yes so Persia itself was Indian but
today historians want to steal
everything away from India and ascribe
it to everybody else to to somebody else
so the neighbor the neighboring
daughter civilization Persia is is is
the best fit for them so even kotan is
Persian even Afghanistan is p everything
is poran they even have something called
Iranian ancestry these days in genetics
so these are simply attempts to try and
um take credit for everything away from
India and it's it's kind of funny and
because it's not going to last forever
you know lies eventually are are
are
caught so um my thoughts I don't care
let them try and do this facts are facts
kotan was founded by Indians it was
Indians kashgar was Indian you know we
want to see where kashgar is let's go
back to to to the
map so hutan is right here it's this
Oasis north of ladak where is kashgar
shall we find kashgar
uh here it is this here is kashgar
further north from kutan to the
northwest of hutan
kashgar do you know what kashgar was
called until the 19th
century until the 19th century kashgar
was called Kashi
nagar all
right kashgar was called Kashi nagar
until the 19th century now it's called
kashgar so a lot of history is lies I
mean if the news is fake imagine his how
fake history is right there you have
it vikor says how did the Spanish
mismanage the immense wealth stolen from
the Americas ultimately weakening their
power compared to the UK and the
France France espia Spain so Spain
plundered a tremendous amount of gold
and wealth from the americ
tremendous amount of wealth gold and
silver from the Americas and this
immense influx of
bullion raw gold and silver from the
Americas it should have made Spain
Europe's wealthiest and most powerful
Nation right and yet it did not this did
not happen Spain never became a
superpower it was a superpower until
this this this whole influx of of gold
started into Spain I mean
when the Spanish Armada tried to invade
um and Conquer England during the reign
of Queen Elizabeth at the time England
was was a second rate world power and
Spain was the great superpow at the time
and yet in 100 years despite all the
immense wealth it plundered from the
natives from the hapless natives of
americaas Spain became a third rate
world power so what happens so what what
happened so there are there's a number
of reasons obviously first of all these
precious metals that the Spanish stole
from the
Americas the Spanish they treated this
as a quick source of Revenue and the
Spanish monarchs use this to finance
their extravagant Lifestyles and their
continuous
Warfare they thought this gold and
silver is just so incredibly abundant
it's flowing like a river from the
Americas
so let's just keep burning that that it
as fuel they did not invest any of it in
local Industries in infrastructure in in
in uh trade
routes in agriculture whatever they
invested
nothing what they did was they kept on
importing manufactured goods from other
from other places in Europe instead of
producing them domestically they never
became a manufacturing economy this
simply thought we have this endless
supply of wealth let's just buy whatever
we want from from other
countries no
foresight and then there was this
chronic Warfare that the Spanish Crown
enjoyed so the Spanish kept fighting
numerous Wars they had Wars in it
against Italy in Netherlands even
against the Ottoman Empire and to have
this continuous Warfare you need a huge
military you need a big Navy you need uh
lots of soldiers you need to hire
mercenaries you need foreign supplies
because you manufacturing nothing so the
Spanish
monarchy spent enormous sums of money to
maintain this Army and this continuous
lifestyle of continuous Warfare so
whatever New Wealth kept on flowing from
the Americas it got drained away almost
as soon as it arrived okay and it's not
just that
they use the wealth from the Americas to
finance their Warfare on top of that the
the Spanish Kings and monarchs they took
huge debts on top of this so this huge
amount of money that's flowing in every
day it's not enough they needed more so
they took big debts multiple times to
finance various Wars and they had to
even declare bankruptcy multiple
times and obviously when you have big
debts you're gonna have uh interest and
so on so forth so doesn't
work and because so much gold was coming
into Spain
uh it
caused significant
inflation in their
economy and what happens is that only
some people have the gold right there's
a lot of gold coming in but it's the
royalty and the nobility who hold the
gold so the prices go up because there's
so much gold in the market now but the
prices go up but what about the peasants
and the poor people they don't have any
gold but the prices have shot up so they
become super poor as a result so the
cost of living soared for the for the
non Royal non- noble people and the cost
of Waging War also also went up and so
on and so on so they did not invest in
manufacturing they did not invest in um
industry they did not invest in trade
routes they did not invest in foreign in
controlling foreign ports nothing
extremely shortsighted they did the
exact opposite of what the English
did so that's why Spain dis you know you
know what you see generally when
somebody wins a
lottery the vast majority of people who
win a big lottery they become broken
into three
years because they've never had wealth
certainly there's this big amount of
money millions of dollars that they have
and they just start splurging it without
any kind of plan and in a in two three
years they go broke and they go back to
their original job if they're lucky so
so that's the kind of approach and
attitude Spain
had and the English were very different
they were very hard-headed in their
approach to to colonizing the
Americas and that's why they succeeded
and if you want to understand this whole
matter watch my understanding America
podcast in which I go into exactly these
things all right um
Aura badage says I've been noticing in
my surroundings that despite being a
relatively proud Indian who's proud of
his culture I would maybe prefer going
to a church at times than a temple me
and my peers could listen to local
Spanish and western songs but would
cringe when we hear loc GS at times and
many more cases I don't know how this
resistiveness has been ingrained into my
blood how do we make the coming
generation be more proud of their
culture I'll tell you why everyone feels
this way it's because everything Indian
has been portrayed as
uncool it's not cool to be Indian it's
not cool to be Hindu a temple is not
cool everything foreign and Western is
cool the Indian accent is not cool the
Spanish accent oh seor is so
cool but the Indian accent is so dirty
oh no no no right the Latino accent is
cool LA isol but the Indian accent is
bad and so on so everything Indian is
portrayed as
uncool Hinduism is portrayed as uncool
and the the system in India ensures that
everything Indian everything indigenous
remains shabby and dirty you go to
Temple premises anywhere you'll find
that the temple authorities have no
money for the upkeep of the temple so
it's shabby
there is no space Sacred Space around
the T Temple there's all kinds of dirt
around the
temple so you don't feel like going to a
temple it's not a very nice environment
to go to m most often it's like that
there are very few temples that are very
clean look at the temples that you see
in Thailand for example Hindu temples
beautifully maintained well painted so
pretty so aesthetic because so much
money goes into the upkeep of the Vishnu
temples and the Hanuman temples and the
fa temples in Thailand look at Hindu
temples in Japan the temples of the Kami
Ben
zitin also known as
sarasti how beautifully they maintained
and look at the same temples of the same
deities in India how poorly they are
maintained
because the money that is donated by
devotes of the temple is stolen by the
government so everything in India when
when it comes to Indian culture Hindu
ISM whatever is
shabby it's in disrepair all our
historical monuments are shabby and in
disrepair the ASI
maintains The Monuments of
Invaders if you go to historical temples
all the all the all the mores have their
faces and arms and various body parts
hacked off
right um there's no promotion of Indian
culture there's no money spent by the
government not enough money spent by the
government to promote talented
artists who would make Indian culture
cool again Indian art cool again the
most profoundly beautiful form of music
in the world today is Indian classical
music with a system of ragas you have no
idea how
incredibly brilliant the system is the
greatest system of music ever devised no
one even knows about it in India all you
need all you know is Bollywood songs and
foreign songs and all so it's because
there has been this this
this uh this push this concerted effort
to make everything Indian
uncool that most people feel this way
what Aura is is mentioning down here
right so how do we make the coming
generation be more proud of their
culture first of all be aware of your
culture recently I mean yeah I might as
well say this this new music video came
out by somebody called Hanuman kind I
had never heard of the guy guy before I
am not into rap music but the music
video is incredible it's awesome the guy
his name is surj something he's from
Kerala and he has made this video which
showcases Indian martial arts Traditions
from various parts of India from from
Maharashtra from Kerala from Manipur
from Punjab indigenous martial arts
Traditions they are so incredibly I mean
breathtaking
and most didn't even know that this this
existed in in India right so we need to
become more aware of our of of of the
incredible beauty and Brilliance of our
culture and the system ensures you don't
do that you don't get that the the we
have the only education system in the
world which doesn't teach children their
own culture and so on so that's why we
are we are detached from our culture we
are deracinated generation after
generation we move further and further
away from our culture so most Indian
kids today they don't know what their
culture is they they see it as something
alien the way a person from England
would see Indian culture that's the way
same way Indians see their culture today
and that's why you would be happier and
more comfortable going to a church and
listening to
thiso or
whatever so yeah we need to make India
Indian culture cool again Aesthetics
matter matter
right so yeah it's work in
progress Nik says I am currently an
18-year-old in Bangalore from Bangalore
do you think it's better for someone
like me to Aspire for a future in Barat
or aspire to immigrate immigrate for say
for example work towards an OV Visa
which is I think it's called a genius
Visa person with outstanding abilities
American visa right I may not be a fan
of the governmental or bureaucratic
establishment but I do love my
motherland how do you see the Indian
landscape in the into the early 30s of
my
generation look India is not going to
change
drastically in the next 20 30 10 20 10
20 years you will not see tremendous
drastic change in reforms in India next
20 years not going to happen the system
is too deeply
entrenched and you will not see big bang
reforms and complete overhaul of the
system um I am glad that uh you do love
your mother motherland and I'm glad to
hear that you're are somebody who
aspires to have something like an ow
Visa the ow Visa is for persons of
extraordinary AB abilities I think it's
also called the Genius level
Visa if you are good enough to get that
I would suggest you go and get the ow
Visa go to the US you don't have to stop
loving Barat your
motherland you can continue loving your
motherland what you can do the next 20
years is go work in the US is acquire
all the experience you can acquire all
the talent Al not Talent all the
experience and all the skills you can
and more importantly all the money you
can become as as wealthy as you
can and then reassess where you are and
where bath is in 20 years time let's say
by the time you're in your late 30s you
are a billionaire let's
say then you may think of coming back to
Barat and serving your motherland
because right now you're an 18-year-old
kid you don't have any real money of
your own obviously no 18-year-old has
any real money and if you stay back in
bhat with your Genius level talent I
think the system will not give a damn
about a talent do you remember Shas ra
ramanujan he was a genius he was nearly
destroyed by the system he is known
today because an English man dis
discovered him if it was in the hands of
the Indian bureaucrats he would have
been destroyed and nobody would have
remembered him so my point is the system
will not care about you the Indian
system is such that it seeks out and
destroys talent and it seeks out and
rewards
mediocrity if you are a person of
extraordinary abilities get the hell out
of
India next 20 years at least become a
billionaire and then if India is ready
for you you may come back at that point
to bat and serve your motherland
so yeah um that's what I would say I'm
glad you love your motherland as we all
do but that's the best course of action
for you in my
opinion okay let's take some questions
from the live chat
now what's going on in the live chat
okay I haven't seen
so all right if you have any questions
that you would like to ask me I will
take some questions from the live chat
at this point in time
uh I already discussed starlink so
there's no point discussing it
again uh I don't know what wellar is so
I will not take
that what is
wiar Rocky Ru says what's
wiar uh Isabella says if you lose your
Indian culture how can we appreciate the
Indian culture in the future that's
right so we should not lose our culture
look the world is beautiful because it's
diverse not because there's all every
culture in the world in one city no no
what makes the world beautiful is that
when you travel from one country to
another you see different cultures
different Lifestyles different ways of
clothing different Cuisines different
music that's what makes the world so
beautiful so I think every culture needs
to have its own space Indian culture in
the
subcontinent uh Spanish culture Flamenco
in Spain French culture in France
Italian culture in Italy Rose the
culture in Russia and so on so forth
various Native American cultures in the
Americas Asian cultures in various parts
of Asia that's what makes the world
beautiful so we need all these cultures
to survive and thrive especially Indian
culture which is probably the oldest
known culture in the world right now so
yeah I agree now what other questions do
we
have
um uh kapalin says what's your view on
Manipur under President rule I think
it's early days it's too early to pass
judgment president's rule is very new in
Manipur and yeah there are problems
right so the the governor had given a
certain deadline for
uh for everyone to lay down their
arms and we know there are two main
ethnic groups right now that are in the
eye of the storm right now the mes the
indigenous people of Manipur the Hindus
and the foreigners the cookie
infiltrators
so apparently the cookies are are not
giving up their arms as for years and
the government has said that there will
be free trans free movement in the state
the cookies are blockading roads and
doing all kinds of violent activities
and stuff so yes there are challenges
right
now and I wonder how much patience the
government of India will have towards
the
foreigners I mean yeah we'll see so
right now I don't have any views it's
too early to say
anything but at some point in time I
think the government of India should act
and do do the right thing for the
citizens
okay uh what else what else what else
what else what
else dasan says any updates on GE
engines and Tes is US delaying this on
purpose to keep if modernization under
control it's a pressure it's a pressure
tactic to over India it's to show that
we have so much leverage over you we can
stop your entire aircraft program
fighter plane program from
progressing it's to delay the Indian Air
Force modernization the thingses is a
very good fighter plane one of the best
fighter planes small fighter planes in
the world but if it doesn't have engines
what will it do what will it do with it
so I don't know about any updates on the
G engines the Americans whether they are
sending more engines or not
uh we need Alternatives we cannot rely
on the
Americans we need to be able to develop
to build engines entirely in India using
only Indian components and
materials which means that we need to
either develop our own engine or have a
complete transfer of Technology from
somewhere wherever from whether it's
Russia whether it's France whether it's
whoever else doesn't matter so we need
that
um MCL says why are we prioritizing man
missions to Mars or exploring our oceans
given that only 20% of the world's
oceans have been
explored well the world is so large out
there and under the oceans we don't
quite know what's there there are some
parts of the oceans where you have uh
resources like uh nickel like iron or
various other minerals and what whatnot
but it's so difficult to go all the way
down there and extract that
and so the ocean the the Sub sub surface
environment of the oceans is a far more
difficult place to explore than maybe
Mars you know that's how it is so
there's multiple reasons including the
fact that it's so difficult to go down
there and and if you go like several
kilometers below the ocean surface
you'll find that the conditions there
are almost alien to us incredible
pressure water pressure at that depth
and the temperatures are very cold and
if you want to survive there you need a
very very specialized submarine your
regular submarines will just
implode uh below a certain depth called
The Crush depth of a submarine so it's
so difficult there's no light down
there so it's almost like an alien
environment so it's it's actually easier
to to explore
uh
other planetary bodies than the sub
ocean environment in some
cases okay
um badass Ravi Kumar says do you trust
China I trust Every
Nation I trust Every Nation to do
whatever is in their best
interests so if you want to know
uh whether to trust a nation or not you
have to understand what is their
perception of their National
interest if you know what's going on in
their minds then you know how they'll
behave and then it's
fine so you can trust Every Nation Every
Nation to to prioritize its National
interest over every other nation's
interests so yeah I trust China to do
that do I trust China to to be our
friend there are no friends in
geopolitics the point is the the
question of trust doesn't arise in
geopolitics you don't trust anybody in
geopolitics you have to understand each
nation and its perception of it of its
interests and when you have two Nations
whose interests converge to some extent
those two Nations can cooperate in a
mutually beneficial manner and when you
have two Nations whose interests are
wildly
diverging and
mutually non-beneficial those two
Nations will never be at good relations
with each other
so from my perspective China is an
independent nation an ancient culture
that has the right to pursue its
National interest and sometimes its
National interest its perception of its
interest will bring it in territory that
is um you could say hostile to India or
conflicting with India so we have to
know that this can happen and this will
happen and we have to take adequate
steps to ensure it doesn't harm us the
question of trust blind trust simply
doesn't arise in geopolitics all
right um abijit cha light says why
cannot we reverse engineer the engine of
the just like you said buy B borrow
steel we can reverse engineer the design
the blueprint okay so let's say we take
one engine we have what 26 Rafal let's
say we we take out one of those Rafal
fighter planes okay and we use it only
for research purposes so we have 25 left
and one Rafal we're going to research do
research on it we open it up we take out
the engine and we dismantle the engine
step by step so that we know how every
single component is designed and built
so then by doing this process and
because we have such talented Engineers
we'll be able to create our own
blueprint of the Rafal jet engine right
jet engine which belongs to a company
called saf I
believe which it's manufactured by saf
so we can create our own blueprint which
can exactly replicate all the components
of this engine and yet it will
fail why will it fail because there is a
technology called single Crystal blade
technology that we don't
have you see the turbine blades inside
the jet engine have to operate at
incredibly High pressures and
temperatures temperatures that will that
will melt
steel so how come these turbine blades
don't melt because they are grown out of
a single Crystal of metal it's an alloy
it's I don't know what nickel something
alloy so it's a single each each turbine
blade is a single
Crystal okay and they have holes and air
vents and stuff inside it's incredibly
difficult to manufacture that it takes
Decades of trial and error to do
that so you can you can create a replica
of that uh jet engine turbine blade
using Steel or whatever metal you have
at your disposal and you put that engine
together and you try and
flight you try and ignite the ignite the
the Jet
Engine and you'll find that the blades
will melt so that's the
problem so yeah we need to acquire the
technology somehow how to um grow those
crystals um Abhijit Supreme Lord says
why is Russia left out in the AI race I
don't know
um as far as we know they have not
announced any any AI system like the
Chinese have with deep seek R1 and Manus
and the Americans with their various
things and the French of mistal the
Russians don't seem to have any AI maybe
they are hiding their capacity
capabilities maybe they have an AI
system or multiple AI systems and they
haven't announced it or maybe they are
genuinely Left Behind if they are
genuinely left behind why is that maybe
because they don't
have access to the chips like the
Chinese and the Americans do the Chinese
can manufacture their own chips the
Russians probably can't so maybe that's
the reason why maybe that's the reason
why and that is not good that is not
good at all so maybe they'll be doing
something about it but nothing is
visible it may be all behind closed
doors okay maybe we can take one more
question um
let's take one more question and then we
will end it end this uh session for
today
um don't know what do I
take okay why only Russia and China have
a space force the Chinese have recently
announced space force recently there was
this news of an asteroid that had a
small probability of hitting the Earth
in 2032 now the probability has gone to
zero but when this news came out in the
public domain the Chinese set up a space
force so the American have space force
the Russians have one and now the
Chinese also have one why don't we have
one
because why do we need
one so only Nations that see themselves
as great powers and nations with great
Ambitions they are the ones who set up
space forces we have all the ability but
we're not doing it uh we should have
space for us I would say all
right and with that I'm going to end
today's session we've all as always
crossed two hours so thank you so much
everybody for all the questions it was
fun taking questions at the end from the
live chat as well and please keep asking
questions and I will and I will take
your questions once again during next
weekend's episode in which I will take
questions only from the live chat as
promised earlier so thank you so much
everybody and take care and keep asking
questions keep raising your standards
and I'll see you very soon in next
week's episode until then take care